Register of the Andrzej Prusiński papers,
Hoover Institution Archives
Andrzej Prusiński papers
1917-2014
2012C10
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, memoranda, bylaws, note cards, and identification documents, relating to the Polish émigré community in Germany.
Prusiński, Andrzej.
Access
Collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Andrzej Prusiński was born on March 18th, 1941 in Kórnik, near the city of Poznań. After completing his primary school education, Prusiński attended secondary school at the renowned Gimnazjum im. Adama Asnyka in Kalisz. In 1959, he graduated and successfully passed the entrance exams for the Astronomy program at the University of Toruń. In 1963, Prusiński relocated from Toruń to Poznań and attended the Adam Mickiewicz University until his graduation in 1966.
It was also in 1966 that Andrzej Prusiński won the Polskie Radio Poznań national competition for radio announcers, which launched his radio career. While at Radio Poznań, Prusiński’s career flourished, as is evident by his work in various capacities: announcer, journalist, and radio broadcaster. He later decided to pursue a professional degree in journalism at the University of Warsaw. Prusiński never completed his degree, because in 1980, along with his wife and daughter, he immigrated to West Germany to pursue a job with the Polish branch of Radio Free Europe (RFE), which he secured in 1982. He worked as a broadcaster with RFE until its closing on June 30th, 1993.
While working for RFE, Prusiński became involved with Zjednoczenie Polskich Uchodźców w Niemczech (Union of Polish Refugees in Germany) and eventually became one of its leaders. He was also appointed as the Member of Parliament in West Germany for the Polish Government-in-exile by the President of Poland-in-exile, Edward Bernard Raczyński.
Prusiński currently resides in Munich, Germany.
Scope and Content
Materials in the collection document the life and career of Andrzej Prusiński. The collection is mainly comprised of: bylaws, correspondence, diaries, émigré documents, Kongres Wolnej Polski w Europie (Free Polish Congress in Europe) documents, Rada Koordynacyjna Polonii Wolnego Świata (Polish Coordination Council of the Free World) documents, Radio Wolna Europa (Radio Free Europe) documents, and materials regarding Zjednoczenie Polskich Uchodźców w Niemczech (Union of Polish Refugees in Germany).
Zjednoczenie Polskich Uchodźców w Niemczech.; Polish people--Germany.
- Bylaws, circa 1950 (Text : 1: 1)
- Diary, 1939-1954 (Text : 1: 2)
- Émigré Index Cards, 1950-1954 (Text : 1: 3-4)
- Greeting Cards, circa 1985 (Text : 1: 5)
- Konfederacja Polski Niepodległej, 1987 (Text : 1: 6)
- Kongres Wolnej Polski w Europie, 1987 (Text : 1: 7)
  Scope and Contents
  The documents in this folder pertain to the Free Polish Congress in Europe and include: news announcements, correspondence, handwriting samples, agreements, confirmation documents, liabilities, and documents explaining the scope of activities and responsibilities of the congressional executive office manager.
  - Aktualności, 1987
  - Correspondence, 1987
  - Handschriftprobe (handwriting sample), circa 1987
  - Porozumienia, 1987
  - Potwierdzenia, 1987
  - Zakres Czynności i Obowiązków Kierownika Biura Wykonawczego, 1987
  - Zobowiązania, 1987
- Powołanie na członka Rady Narodowej Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej, 1983-1984 (Text : 1: 8)
- "Praca Sprawozdawczy Sportowego,", October 17-26, 1950 (Text : 1: 9)
- Rada Koordynacyjna Polonii Wolnego Świata, 1987 (Text : 1: 10)
  Composed of the Polish Coordination Council of the Free World materials: bulletins, membership information, and tentative programming.
  - Biuletyn Informacyjny, October 1987
  - Membership information, circa 1987
  - Tentatywny program, 1987
- Radio Wolna Europa, 1975-2014
  Contains Radio Free Europe documents: correspondence, materials regarding the 1993 closing of the Polish branch of RFE, proposal for the creation of a Polish Radio in Europe, regulations manual for employees, and information regarding the Polish archives' efforts to collect RFE materials.
  - Correspondence, 1985-2014 (Text : 1: 11)
  - Pożegnanie Radio Wolna Europa, 1994 (Text : 1: 12)
  - Propozycja utworzenia Rozgłośni Polskiej "Europa,", 1995 (Text : 1: 13)
  - Regulamin Pracy pracowników zatrudnionych w Komitecie d/s Radia i Telewizji, 1975 (Text : 1: 14)
  - Shortwaves, 1992 (Text : 1: 15)
  - Uroczystość podpisania umowy między naczelną dyrekcją archiwów państwowych a Radiem Wolna Europa - Radiem Swoboda, 1996 (Text : 1: 16)
- "Rok Polski: 50-lecie najazdu na Polskę," C. Zychowicz, 1987 (Text : 1: 17)
- Stowarzyszenie Polskich Kombatantów, 1981-1985 (Text : 1: 18)
- Zaświadczenie - Szkoła Przedmiotów Ojczystych, circa 1980 (Text : 1: 19)
- Zjednoczenie Polskich Uchodźców w Niemczech, 1972-1987
  Comprised of materials produced by the Union of Polish Refugees in Germany: employment contracts and documents, registers, statutes, agreements, liabilities, and announcements.
  - Anstellungsvertrag (employment contract), 1987 (Text : 1: 20)
  - Biuro Porad i Interwencji, circa 1980 (Text : 1: 21)
  - Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Text : 1: 22)
  - Employment documents, 1987 (Text : 1: 23)
  - Główna Komisja Rewizyjna, 1987 (Text : 1: 24)
  - Mietvertrag (dorm lease), 1987 (Text : 1: 25)
  - Obowiązki, 1987 (Text : 1: 26)
  - Ocena Prawomocności Uchwał Zarządu Głównego, 1987 (Text : 1: 27)
  - Porozumienia, 1987 (Text : 1: 28)
  - Potwiedzenia, 1987 (Text : 1: 29)
  - Regulamin Obrad, 1985 (Text : 1: 30)
  - Regulamin Pracy Zarządu Głuwnego ZPU, circa 1987 (Text : 1: 31)
  - Rejstracje, 1987 (Text : 1: 32)
  - Satzung (statute), 1985 (Text : 1: 33)
  - Sąd Koleżeński, 1987 (Text : 1: 34)
  - Wyciąg z Protokołu Zebrania Prezydium Zarządu Głównego, 1987 (Text : 1: 35)
  - Zawiadomienia, 1987 (Text : 1: 36)
  - Zobowiązania, 1987 (Text : 1: 37)
  - 20 Jahre des Verbandes Polnischer Flüchtlinge, March 19, 1972 (Text : 1: 38)
- Zjednoczenie Polskie w Wielkiej Brytanii, circa 1987 (Text : 1: 39)
- Zofia Ogonowska (Odrobna), 1917-1950 (Text : 1: 40)